Guide to the Bradley T. Johnson Papers, 1829-1903 RL.10123
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Bradley T. Johnson papers
1851-1909
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Johnson, Bradley T.
RL.10123
2 Linear Feet 4 boxes (922 items)
Bradley T. Johnson was a Confederate officer, lawyer, and politician, born in Frederick (Frederick Co.), Maryland who later settled in Virginia after the Civil War. The collection includes correspondence, personal accounts, Civil War reminiscences of campaigns in several states, a memoir of the 1st Maryland Regiment, C.S.A., a muster roll of the 21st Virginia, Company B, records of a Confederate prison hospital, and an incomplete diary of a trip to Cuba as correspondent during the Spanish-American War. Included also are a series of letters from Wade Hampton and from Joseph E. Johnston. Other correspondents include Henry Adams, James Cardinal Gibbons, and Henry Cabot Lodge along with an anonymous April-Dec., 1846 diary, identified with Isaac R. Watkins, law student in Richmond, Va. and son of prosperous Charlotte County family.
Collection Overview
Correspondence, personal accounts, Civil War reminiscences of campaigns in Virginia, Maryland, and Pennsylvania of Bradley T. Johnson, a Confederate officer, lawyer, and politician, born in Frederick (Frederick Co.), Md. who later settled in Virginia after the Civil War. The collection also includes a memoir of the 1st Maryland Regiment, C.S.A., a muster roll of the 21st Virginia, Company B, records of a Confederate prison hospital, and an incomplete diary of a trip to Cuba as correspondent during the Spanish-American War. It includes a series of letters from Wade Hampton and from Joseph E. Johnston. Other correspondents include Henry Adams, James Cardinal Gibbons, and Henry Cabot Lodge.
Collection also Includes anonymous April-Dec., 1846 diary, identified with Isaac R. Watkins, a law student in Richmond, Va. and son of a prosperous Charlotte County family.
Biographical note
Bradley T. Johnson (1829-1903), was a Confederate officer, lawyer, and politician, born in Frederick (Frederick Co.), Md. who later settled in Virginia after the Civil War.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Hospitals -- Confederate States of America; Spanish-American War, 1898 -- Journalists; Maryland -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Diaries -- Lawyers -- Virginia; Pennsylvania -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Campaigns; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Personal narratives; Virginia -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Lodge, Henry Cabot; Watkins, Isaac R.; Johnson, Bradley T.; Johnston, Joseph E. (Joseph Eggleston); Confederate States of America. Army. Maryland Infantry Regiment, 1st; Gibbons, James; Confederate States of America. Army. Virginia Infantry Regiment, 21st (Company B); Hampton, Wade; Adams, Henry
- Bradley T. Johnson Papers, 1829-1903
  - Correspondence, 1851-1909 and undated; 8 folders (Box 1)
  - Quartermaster's papers, 1864-1865; 1 folders (Box 2)
  - Telegrams, 1865; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Print materials, clippings, pictures, etc., undated; 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Writings, "Memoir of the 1st Maryland Regiment", undated; 1 folders (Box 3)
  - Isaac R. Watkin's Diary, 1846; 1 folders (Box 3)
  - Writings, Expedition against Sioux, 1876; 1 folders (Box 3)
  - Other writings, undated; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Other writings and documents, undated; 6 folders (Box 4)
  - Diary, 1896 (Volume M:1947)
    General Note
    The diary is entitled 'Adventures of a War Correspondent." Entries from May 21-July 11, 1896. Card catalog "Diary of a jaunt to Cuba: incomplete and inconsequential."